@是P於你的故事
This is a story about you
也P於我和你的狗
and me and your dog.
不久之前  在狗出F之前
There was a time not long ago... before dogs.
他以前不存在
They didn't exist.
F在的狗有大有小 物狗
Now there are big ones, small ones, snugglers,
守o犬  C犬
guardians, hunters.
各式各拥墓
Every kind of dog you could possibly want.
怎N@
How did that happen?
不HH是狗
It's not just dogs.
形形色色的各N生物
Where did all the different kinds
都是哪难Y淼哪
of living creatures come from?
答案是碜阅芰康霓DQ  上去可能
The answer is a transforming power that sounds like something
像是童或者神
straight out of a fairy tale or myth,
但K非如此
but it's no such thing.
宇宙大探索
第二集
我回到3f年前 狗狗Q生前
Let's go back across 30,000 years to a time before dogs,
那是我的祖先生活在最後一次冰河r代的oM冬夜
when our ancestors lived in the endless winter of the last ice age.
我的祖先小模的群居 [著
Our ancestors were wanderers living in small bands.
他睡在星空下
They slept beneath the stars.
星星就是他的故事  日
The sky was their storybook, calendar,
生活指南
an instruction manual for living.
星星告V他篮何r到
It told them when the bitter colds would come,
Y物何r成熟
when the wild grains would ripen,
鹿群和野牛群何rw徙
when the herds of caribou and bison would be on the move.
他家的印象就是地球本身
Their idea of home was Earth itself.
但是他受到其他|I生物的威But they lived in fear of other hungry creatures...
比如the mountain lions and the bears
c他Z同拥孬C物
that competed with them for the same prey
有狼群掠食他中
and the wolves that threatened to carry off and devour
最脆弱的同伴
the most vulnerable among them.
所有的狼都想矸忠槐羹
All the wolves want to get at the bone,
但大部分都不敢靠的太近
but most of them are too frightened to come close enough.
他的恐碜匝液中
Their fear is due to high levels
高舛鹊激激素
of stress hormones in their blood.
@是生死攸P的}
It's a matter of survival.
因榭康奶近可能很致命
Because coming too close to humans can be fatal.
但也有些狼  因樽匀徊町
But a few wolves-- due to natural variations--
@N激素舛容^低
have lower levels of those hormones.
使得他不是那N峙氯祟
This makes them less afraid of humans.
@^狼和他祖先
This wolf has discovered
中的一分支lF了同拥那r
what a branch of his ancestors figured out
大s在1f5千年前
some 15,000 years ago...
一完美的生存策略
an excellent survival strategy;
人的Z化
the domestication of humans.
在人捕Cre威Let the humans do the hunting, don't threaten them,
他允S你以渣槭
and they'll let you scavenge their garbage.
你吃的更律 就可以繁衍更多的後代
You'll eat more regularly, you'll leave more offspring,
@些後代^承你的性情
and those offspring will inherit your disposition.
@NZB的淘汰方式
This selection for tameness
效果逐代加
would be reinforced with each generation
直到@一系的野狼M化
until that line of wild wolves evolves into...
狗
dogs.
你可以Q它樽钣焉频纳存
You might call this "survival of the friendliest."
F在看 @也是θ祟非常有利的
Then as now, this was a good deal for the humans, too.
那些吃剩的狗K不只是收拾垃圾
The scavenging dogs weren't just a sanitation squad.
他也是保安力量
They worked security.
S著@N不同物Ng的合作
As this interspecies partnership continued over time,
狗的外貌也l生了改
the dogs' appearance changed also.
可圩成了倭犹r的
Cuteness became a selective advantage.
你越可 就有更大的C活下去
The more adorable you were, the better chance you had
K把你的基因鬟fo下一代
to live and pass on your genes to another generation.
起先是榱吮憷而Y成的盟
What began as an alliance of convenience
成了越碓缴詈竦挠颜x
became a friendship that deepened over time.
接下戆l生了什N
To see what happens next,
我略^2f年前的先祖
let's leave our distant ancestors
看看不是很久以前的古人
of some 20,000 years ago to visit the more recent past
在冰河r代的g歇期
during an intermission in the Ice Age.
平和的夂砹艘鲎革
This break in the climate starts a revolution.
人不再流浪  而是定居下
Instead of wandering, people are settling down.
新的事物出F了  村f
There's something new in the world... villages.
人依然在打C和窦食物
People still hunt and gather,
但也_始了u造食物和衣服
but now they also produce food and clothing...
rI
agriculture.
狼用他的自由
The wolves have traded their freedom
斫Q定的食物供
in exchange for a steady meal.
他放了x疋钒榈嗬
They've given up their right to choose a mate.
人替他x
Now the humans choose for them.
他消o法被Z服的狗
They consistently kill off the dogs that can't be trained;
那些咬人的狗
the ones that bite the feeding hand.
他繁育那些喜的狗
And they breed the dogs that please them.
@些狗服拿令
They nurture those dogs that do their bidding...
打C  放牧  守l  拖拽重物
hunting, herding, guarding, hauling,
陪伴人
and keeping them company.
拿恳桓C小狗中
From every litter,
x衲切┧最喜g的
the humans select the puppies they like best.
一代接一代 狗M化了
Over the generations, the dogs evolve.
Q之 人工x
This kind of evolution is called "artificial selection"
或者  B
or "breeding."
把狼成狗 是人第一次
Turning wolves into dogs was the first time
H手干AM化^程
we humans took evolution into our own hands.
哪且葬嵛改M了
And we've been doing it ever since
ξ有用的植物和游
to shape all the plants and animals that we depend on.
指一]g 大s1f5千到2f年Y
In a blink of cosmic time, just 15,000 or 20,000 years,
我把灰狼改成榱
we turned gray wolves into all the kinds of dogs
各N各拥目鄣墓
we love today.
想想看
Think of it.
各品N的狗
Every breed of dog you've ever seen
都是人塑造出淼
was sculpted by human hands.
其中大部分 最受g迎的品N
Many of our best friends-- the most popular breeds--
都是最近装倌昱嘤出淼
were created in only the last few centuries.
M化的大力量
The awesome power of evolution
⒏FO旱睦
transformed the ravenous wolf
成忠心耿耿的牧羊犬
into the faithful shepherd...
保o 看守羊群 Ks狼群
...who protects the herd and drives the wolf away.
人工培育 把狼成狗
Artificial selection turned the wolf into the shepherd
把野草成小和玉米
and the wild grasses into wheat and corn.
事上 大部分我食用的植物和游
In fact, almost every plant and animal that we eat today
都是碜砸吧的 不可食用的品N
was bred from a wild, less-edible ancestor.
如果大的人工x窨梢栽1f到1f5千年g
If artificial selection can work such profound changes
砣绱司薮蟮淖化
in only 10,000 or 15,000 years,
那N大自然的x裉蕴
what can natural selection do
在上百f年g可以做到怎拥某潭饶
operating over billions of years?
形形色色美好的生命就是答案
The answer is all the beauty and diversity of life.
怎N做到得
How does it work?
我的想像之舟可以我去任何地方
Our Ship of the Imagination can take us anywhere in space
任何rg 甚至看不的小宇宙
and time, even to the hidden microcosmos,
在哪Y 生命可以完成
where one kind of life can be transformed into another.
跟我
Come with me.
看上去可能不像
May not seem like it,
我曾生活在冰河r期
but we've been living in an ice age
L_2百f年之久
for the last two million years.
F在只是其中一g歇期
This just happens to be one of the long intermissions.
2百f年g的大部分r期
For most of those two million years,
夂蛴掷溆指
the climate has been cold and dry.
北O冰w比今天
The North Polar ice cap extended much farther south
所看到的更大
than it does today.
在@漫L的冰川期
In one of those long, cold glacial periods
谋O淼亩季海水冰
when the winter sea ice stretched from the North Pole
一直延伸至今日洛杉所在的位置
all the way down to what is now Los Angeles,
大灰熊在冰龌氖的m[
great bears roamed the frozen wastes of Ireland.
@^熊看上去很普通
This might look like an ordinary bear,
但是她的仍s有著不平凡的化
but something extraordinary is happening inside her.
一股催生新物N的力量
Something that will give rise to a new species.
要探究@股力量
In order to see it,
我要把比例尺we'll need to descend down to a much smaller scale,
胞e
to the cellular level,
@硬拍芴骄啃艿纳殖系y
so that we can explore the bear's reproductive system.
我通^i骨下的用}穿^心K
We'll take the subclavian artery through the heart.
快到了
Almost there.
那是一些她的卵子
Those are some of her eggs.
要想t解@些卵子的情
To see what's going on in one of them,
我必得更小
we'll have to get even smaller.
s小到分子e
We'll have to shrink down to the molecular level.
我的想像之舟有多小呢
Our Ship of the Imagination is now so small,
只有一w沙粒的百f分之一
you could fit a million of them into a grain of sand.
看到那些步前M的小砘
See those guys over there strutting along those girders?
他是蛋白| 叫做拥鞍
They are proteins called kinesin.
@些拥鞍资前徇\工
These kinesin are part of the transport crew
忙碌地在胞g鬟f物
that's busy moving cargo around the cell.
L得就像外星人
How alien they seem.
他和其他L相似的小砘
And yet these tiny creatures-- and beings like them--
存在於每活胞中 包括我的胞
are a part of every living cell, including the ones inside you.
如果生命w也有}殿
If life has a sanctuary,
那就是胞核 包含了我的
it's here in the nucleus which contains our DNA...
我z髅艽a的h古}
the ancient scripture of our genetic code.
由所有生命w都能理解的Z言成
And it's written in a language that all life can read.
DNA是一NL螺旋A梯畹姆肿
DNA is a molecule shaped like a long twisted ladder
也叫p螺旋Y
or double helix.
A梯的Mn是由4N
The rungs of the ladder are made
不同的小分子M成
of four different kinds of smaller molecules.
@些就是基因字母表中的字母
These are the letters of the genetic alphabet.
@些字母的特定排列M合
Particular arrangements of those letters spell out
a生出λ有生命w的指令
the instructions for all living things,
告V他如果生L 移 消化
telling them how to grow, move, digest,
感知h境 K合 繁殖
sense the environment, heal, reproduce.
DNAp螺旋就是一台分子C器
The DNA double helix is a molecular machine
由1千|Q之樵子的部件M成
with about 100 billion parts called "atoms."
DNA分子中的原子盗
There are as many atoms in a single molecule of your DNA
多的就像y河系中的繁星盗
as there are stars in a typical galaxy.
和狗一
The same is true for dogs
和熊一
and bears
和所有生物一
and every living thing.
我 每一人 就是一小宇宙
We are, each of us, a little universe.
DNA信息在胞c胞g
The DNA message handed down from cell to cell
也在一代接一代的繁衍中常慎地}u著
and from generation to generation is copied with extreme care.
一l_的蛋白|分_p螺旋的l
The birth of a new DNA molecule begins when an unwinding protein
拆_中g的Mn
separates the two strands of the double helix,
新的DNA分子就Q生了
breaking the rungs apart.
胞核的液w中
Inside the liquid of the nucleus,
z髅艽a的分子字母自由的游
the molecular letters of the genetic code float freely.
p螺旋的其中一}u著失去的另外一
Each strand of the helix copies its lost partner,
成完全一拥DNA分子
resulting in two identical DNA molecules.
@就是生命w如果繁衍和鬟f基因
That's how life reproduces genes and transmits them
代代相
from one generation to the next.
一活胞分裂成
When a living cell divides in two,
每胞都в幸环萃暾的
each one takes away with it a complete copy of the DNA.
一N特定的蛋白|校
A specialized protein proofreads to make sure
_保只接受正_的字母
that only the right letters are accepted
@保C了DNA的蚀_}u
so that the DNA is accurately copied.
但是]有什N是完美的
But nobody's perfect.
偶 校σl生失`
Occasionally, a proofreading error slips through,
在z髦噶钪挟a生了微的SC化
making a small, random change in the genetic instructions.
@^熊的卵子胞中l生了突
A mutation has occurred in the bear's egg cell.
如此微的SC事件也
A random event as tiny as this one can have consequences
很大的影
on a far grander scale.
突改了控制毛皮色的基因
That mutation altered the gene that controls fur color.
它影了@只熊的後代的深色毛皮的a生
It will affect the production of dark pigment in the fur
of the bear's offspring.
大多低蛔是o害的
Most mutations are harmless.
有些是致命的
Some are deadly.
少 倥既 使得某生物
But a few, purely by chance, can give an organism
在中@得重大
a critical advantage over the competition.
1年後
A year has passed.
@只熊做了母H
Our bear is now a mother.
作橥蛔的Y果
And as a result of that mutation,
其中一b熊生砭褪前咨的皮毛
one of her two cubs was born with a white coat.
呻b熊L大到可以自己C食r
When the cubs get old enough to venture out on their own,
哪^熊更可能
which bear is more likely
悄悄地接近他的C物
to be able to sneak up on unsuspecting prey?
棕熊和雪^e明@  很h就能被察X
The brown bear can be seen against the snow a mile away.
白熊子OM堂 K把他特的基因
The white bear prospers and passes on
鬟f下去
its own particular set of genes.
@拥那r不喟l生
This happens repeatedly.
再接下去的状Y
Over succeeding generations,
白色皮毛的基因散播遍及整北O的熊
the gene for white fur spreads through the entire population of Arctic bears.
深色皮毛的基因消亡在
The gene for dark fur loses out
生存的中
in the competition for survival.
突是完全SCK且r刻l生的
Mutations are entirely random and happen all the time.
但是h境Κ钅切
But the environment rewards those
ι存有利的突
that increase the chance for survival.
大自然x衲切┛梢愿好mh境的生物
It naturally selects the living things that are better suited to survive.
@Nx窠^Σ皇请SC的
And that selection is the opposite of random.
N群的熊各自分_
The two populations of bears separated,
^了上千年
and over thousands of years,
M化出各自有的特徵
evolved other characteristics that set them apart.
他成了不同的物N
They became different species.
@就是查斯 _文所f的
That's what Charles Darwin meant
物N起源
by "the origin of species."
的熊不M化
An individual bear doesn't evolve;
一群熊在状繁衍中M化
the population of bears evolves over generations.
如果北O的冰日益p少
If the Arctic ice continues to dwindle
全球暖的故 北O熊可能缃^
due to global warming, the polar bears may go extinct.
他被棕熊取代
They'll be replaced by brown bears,
可以更好地m冰融後的h境
better adapted to the now defrosted environment.
@故事和狗的M化不一
This is a different story from the one about the dogs.
]有人去指н@化
No breeder guided these changes.
他都是由自然h境x竦
Instead, the environment itself selects them.
@就是物天
This is evolution by natural selection,
科Wv史上最覆性的理
the most revolutionary concept in the history of science.
1859年 _文首次提出了支持@理的C
Darwin first presented the evidence for this idea in 1859.
它淼h奈聪退
The uproar it caused has never subsided.
槭颤N
Why?
我都可以理解那N令人不m的刺痛
We all understand the twinge of discomfort
我是由猩猩M化而淼
at the thought that we share a common ancestor with the apes.
在我的想法Y H戚 最能我感到G
No one can embarrass you like a relative.
我的近H  黑猩猩
Our closest ones, the chimpanzees,
他l繁在公共龊献龀霾划的e止
they frequently behave inappropriately in public.
人想和他保持距x
There's an understandable human need
也是可以理解的
to distance ourselves from them.
鹘y信仰的核心前提
A central premise of traditional belief
我是造物者特u的
is that we were created separately
和其他游镉^e的
from all the other animals.
@N^c也很容易被理解
It's easy to see why this idea has taken hold.
它我X得 c不同
It makes us feel... special.
如果我和@些涫怯H戚呢
But what about our kinship with the trees?
你又作何感想
How does that make you feel?
@是橡DNA的一部分
Okay, here's a segment of the oak tree's DNA.
把它看做l形a
Think of it like a bar code.
生命代a的指令
The instructions written in the code of life
告V@淙绾畏纸馓欠
tell the tree how to metabolize sugar.
拿它和我自己的DNA作比^
Now let's compare it with the same section of my own DNA.
DNA不撒e
The DNA doesn't lie.
@棵渚褪俏沂散已久的表H
This tree and me-- we're long-lost cousins.
不问
And it's not just the trees.
如果回到很久以前 我可以lF
If you go back far enough, you'll find that we share
我有著共同的祖先
a common ancestor with...
蝴蝶
the butterfly...
灰狼
gray wolf...
蘑菇
mushroom...
~
shark...
菌
bacterium...
麻雀
sparrow.
多N幸福的一家人
What a family!
l形a的其他部分因人而
Other parts of the bar code vary from species to species.
@也使得^和章~有所^e
That's what makes the difference between an owl and an octopus.
除非你有一同卵p胞胎
Unless you have an identical twin,
@世界上不有人
there's no one else in the universe
和你有著相同的
with the exact same DNA as you.
其他的物N中 z骰因的不同
Within other species, the genetic differences
樽匀贿x裉峁┝嗽材料
provide the raw material for natural selection.
h境Q定了什N基因可以生存繁衍
The environment selects which genes survive and multiply.
f到生物z骰因的指令中
When it comes to the genetic instructions for life's
最基本的功能
most basic functions--
比方f分解糖分  我和其他物N
say, digesting sugars-- we and other species
缀跻恢
are almost identical.
因檫@些是生命最基本的功能
That's because those functions are so basic to life,
他在各N不同生命形式Q生前
they evolved before the various life-forms
就已M化完成
branched off from each other.
@就是我的生命之
This is our Tree of Life.
科W使我可以
Science has made it possible
榈厍蛏系乃有生物
for us to construct this family tree
Lu@份家V
for all the species of life on Earth.
相近基因的H戚住在同一根的枝稚
Close genetic relatives occupy the same branch of the tree,
差越大住得越h
while more distant cousins are farther away.
每根枝都是一物N
Each twig is a living species.
主U代表著地球上所有生命的
And the trunk of the tree represents the common ancestors
共同祖先
of all life on Earth.
生命具有很高的可塑性
The stuff of life is so malleable
生命一旦出F  h境就_始
that once it got started, the environment molded it
⑺塑造出@人盗康牟煌形B
into a staggering variety of forms--
比我所能展示的多1f倍
10,000 times more than we can possibly show here.
生物W家已了
Biologists have catalogued
50fN不同的甲はx
a half a million different kinds of beetles alone.
更e提那些抵不M的菌
Not to mention the numberless varieties of bacteria.
有装偃fN不同N的
There are many millions of living species
游锖椭参  其中大部分依然未知
of animals and plants,  most of them still unknown to science.
@Nf吧  我至今]有^
Think of that-- we have yet to make contact
大部分的生物
with most of the forms of terrestrial life.
我@小小星球上就是有@N多N的生命
That's how many kinds of life there are on this tiny planet alone.
生命之⒂|角伸向所有的方向
The Tree of Life extends its feelers in all directions,
探た尚械霓k法
finding and exploiting what works,
樾碌纳命形式造新的h境和C
creating new environments and opportunities for new forms.
生命之湟呀35|q了
The Tree of Life is three and a half billion years old.
rg已L的可以l展出
That's plenty of time to develop
所有令人@奇的本I
an impressive repertoire of tricks.
M化可以使一N游
Evolution can disguise an animal
窝b成植物
as a plant...
花M了登Т的努力
...taking thousands of generations
去O一套精心u作的服
to contrive an elaborate costume
用砥垓_捕食者的眼睛
that fools predators into looking elsewhere for someone to eat.
或者植物窝b成游锏哪
Or it can disguise a plant as an animal,
花朵M化出S蜂般的外表
evolving blossoms that take on the appearance of a wasp--
m花就用@N方式T使S蜂樗授粉
the orchid's way of fooling real wasps into pollinating it.
@就是大的
This is the awesome
自然x裣碌淖形本I
shape-shifting power of natural selection.
在密集sy的巨大生命之渖
Among the dense, tangled limbs of the vast Tree of Life...
你在@Y
you are here.
挡档谋多分支中的一小支
One tiny branch among countless millions.
科W揭示了所有生命本是同源
Science reveals that all life on Earth is one.
_文lF真正的M化C制
Darwin discovered the actual mechanisof evolution.
^去普遍的^c是
The prevailing belief was that the complexity
N繁多的生命必然是有造物主造的
and variety of life must be the work of an intelligent designer,
分e造了装偃fN不同的生物
who created each of these millions of different species separately.
它J 生物在是太}s了
Living things are just too intricate, it was said,
不可能由未引У倪M化而
to be the result of unguided evolution.
就像人的眼睛
Consider the human eye,
一O其}s的茏
a masterpiece of complexity.
要有角膜
It requires a cornea,
虹膜 晶铙w W膜
iris, lens, retina,
神 肌肉群
optic nerves, muscles,
再配合大X}u的神Wj
let alone the brain's elaborate neural network
才能a生一幅D像
to interpret images.
它h比其他任何一人u造的
It's more complicated than any device
物w要淼难}s
ever crafted by human intelligence.
所以 Y是
Therefore, it was argued,
人眼不可能是o意R的
the human eye can't be the result
M化a物
of mindless evolution.
要t解真相 我需要回到
To know if that's true, we need to travel across time
我有能力看之前
to a world before there were eyes to see.
最初 所有生物都看不任何|西
In the beginning, life was blind.
@是我的世界 40|年前的幼
This is what our world looked like four billion years ago,
那r 生物o法a生X
before there were any eyes to see.
直到|年^去
Until a few hundred million years passed,
突然有一天
and then, one day,
一菌的DNAa生了
there was a microscopic copying error
微的}ue`
in the DNA of a bacterium.
@SC的突o了@微生物
This random mutation gave that microbe
一可以吸收光的蛋白|分子
a protein molecule that absorbed sunlight.
想知道感光菌的世界
Want to know what the world looked like
是什N幼拥
to a light-sensitive bacterium?
看看屏幕的右
Take a look at the right side of the screen.
突^mSC的l生
Mutations continued to occur at random,
在其他所有的生物身上
as they always do in any population of living things.
另一突
Another mutation
使得菌可以逃x烈的光
caused a dark bacterium to flee intense light.
l生了什N事
What is going on here?
黑夜和白
Night and day.
@些可以^分亮光的菌
Those bacteria that could tell light from dark
相ζ渌菌有了一Q定性的
had a decisive advantage over the ones that couldn't.
槭颤N
Why?
因槿展е烈的紫外pDNA
Because the daytime brought harsh, ultraviolet light that damages DNA.
敏感的菌避_烈的光
The sensitive bacteria fled the intense light
在暗安全的交Q
to safely exchange their DNA in the dark.
他比其他生活在表面的菌
They survived in greater numbers
更多的存活下
than the bacteria that stayed at the surface.
日e月累 @些光敏蛋白|
Over time, those light-sensitive proteins
在更高的渭胞生物身上
became concentrated in a pigment spot
饪s成一色素c
on the more advanced, one-celled organism.
@使ふ夜饬脸榭赡
This made it possible to find the light,
於需要光合成食物的
an overwhelming advantage
生命w碚f @是旱剐缘
for an organism that harvests sunlight to make food.
@是扁平x眼中的世界
Here's a flatworm's-eye view of the world.
@多胞生物
This multi-celled organism
在色素c中M化出一小坑
evolved a dimple in the pigment spot.
碗畹陌己
The bowl-shaped depression
使游锟梢^e明暗
allowed the animal to distinguish light from shadow
大致看出周的物w
to crudely make out objects in its vicinity,
包括食物和天
including those to eat and those that might eat it...
非常了不起的
a tremendous advantage.
S後 影像更清晰了
Later, things became a little clearer.
小坑深了
The dimple deepened
M化成一有_口的凹槽
and evolved into a socket with a small opening.
^浊Т
Over thousands of generations,
自然x裰u塑造出眼睛
natural selection was slowly sculpting the eye.
_放的地方凝聚成一小孔
The opening contracted to a pinhole covered
由一颖Ｗo性的透明薄膜覆w
by a protective transparent membrane.
只允S一cc的光透^小孔
Only a little light could enter the tiny hole,
但也足蛟诿舾械难劬炔勘砻
but it was enough to paint a dim image
描L出一幅模糊的D像
on the sensitive inner surface of the eye.
@演出了聚焦
This sharpened the focus.
更大的孔可以更多的光通^
A larger opening would have let in more light
a生更亮的D像  但s失去了焦c
to make a brighter image but one that was out of focus.
@新形B引l了
This development launched the visual equivalent
X的涓
of an arms race.
者需要跟上才能生存
The competition needed to keep up to survive.
一新的^妙特徵出F了
But then a splendid new feature of the eye evolved,
可以同r保C亮度和清晰焦c的晶铙w
a lens that provided both brightness and sharp focus.
在h古的~眼中
In the eyes of primitive fish,
小孔附近的透明zw形成了晶铙w
the transparent gel near the pinhole formed into a lens.
同r 小孔U大了
At the same time, the pinhole enlarged
允S更多的光通^
to let in more and more light.
~的界高清了
Fish could now see in high-def,
不h近
both close up and far away.
然而 可怕的事情l生了
And then something terrible happened.
你注意到一杯水中的吸管
Have you ever noticed that a straw in a glass of water
看上去在水面是的
looks bent at the surface of the water?
那是因楣饩囊介|M入另一介|rl生了折射
That's because light bends when it goes from one medium
就像乃到空
to another, say from water to air.
我的眼睛最初是榱嗽谒中物
Our eyes originally evolved to see in water.
眼中的水钜后w巧妙地
The watery fluid in those eyes neatly
消除了折射的影
eliminated the distortion of that bending effect.
但是於地游
But for land animals,
在空庵谐上竦墓饩
the light carries images from dry air
M入他的眼睛
into their still-watery eyes.
光l生折射
That bends the light rays,
造成全面的失真
causing all kinds of distortions.
我的祖先乃中登r
When our amphibious ancestors left the water for the land,
原本在水中精_物的眼睛
their eyes, exquisitely evolved to see in water,
s在空庵幸凰糊T
were lousy for seeing in the air.
哪r起我的力一直不好
Our vision has never been as good since.
我一直J槲的眼睛是最高的
We like to think of our eyes as state-of-the-art,
但直到3.75|年後
but 375 million years later,
我依然o法看清近在眼前的|西
we still can't see things right in front of our noses
或者像~那釉诨璋淡h境中
or discern fine details in near darkness
能虮e
the way fish can.
我x_水Yr
When we left the water,
槭颤N大自然不能男磉^
why didn't nature just start over again
M化出一π碌难劬
and evolve us a new set of eyes
可以在空庵星逦物
that were optimal for seeing in the air?
大自然K不是@拥
Nature doesn't work that way.
M化^程於已有的Y的改
Evolution reshapes existing structures over generations,
是世世代代的慢慢m
adapting them with small changes.
而不可能一切都
It can't just go back to the drawing board
推倒重
and start from scratch.
M化中眼睛 在每一步的l展中
At every stage of its development, the evolving eye
都槲的生存提供了O大的
functioned well enough to provide a selective advantage for survival.
在F在存活的游锷砩 我lF了
And among animals alive today, we find eyes
各l展A段的眼睛
at all these stages of development.
他都很用
And all of them function.
人眼睛的}s程度M化^程碚f
The complexity of the human eye poses
]有z毫y度
no challenge to evolution by natural selection.
事上 ]有M化就根本o法解眼睛和其他生物W
In fact, the eye and all of biology makes no sense without evolution.
有人fM化只是一N理
Some claim that evolution is just a theory,
只不^是一N^c
as if it were merely an opinion.
M化就和f有引力定律一
The theory of evolution, like the theory of gravity,
是科W的事
is a scientific fact.
M化_有其事
Evolution really happened.
承J我和其他生物出自同源
Accepting our kinship with all life on Earth
K不只是乐的科W
is not only solid science.
在我看 @也是一N崇高的心`w
In my view, it's also a soaring spiritual experience.
因檫M化是盲目地
Because evolution is blind,
它o法Ay或改悲〉陌l生
it cannot anticipate or adapt to catastrophic events.
生命之溆幸恍嗔训姆种
The Tree of Life has some broken branches.
其中大部分l生在
Many of them were severed in the five greatest catastrophes
五次最大的碾y中
that life has ever known.
某地方 有著一座o念堂
Somewhere, there's a memorial
o念著消失的物N
to the multitude of lost species,
缃^物N的o念堂
the Halls of Extinction.
S我
Come with me.
缃^o念堂
g迎淼缃^o念堂
Welcome to the Halls of Extinction.
o念著生命之渖系嘀
A monument to the broken branches of the Tree of Life.
於依然存在的上百fN生物碚f
For every single one of the millions of species
可能上千N正在垂死暝
alive today, perhaps a thousand others have perished.
他中大部分在c
Most of them died out in the everyday competition
其他生命形式的日常中^N
with other life-forms.
但也有很多是被地球上
But many of them were swept away in vast cataclysms
o法抗拒的大碾y缃^
that overwhelmed the planet.
在^去的5|年Y
In the last 500 million years,
l生^5次
this has happened five times.
W陶o(地|r代中@生宙古生代的第二o)
5次缃^地球生命的大碾y
Five mass extinctions that devastated life on Earth.
泥盆o(地|r代古生代中的第四o)
三Bo(中生代的第一o)
最K的一次l生在2.5|年前
The worst one of all happened some 250 million years ago,
白准o(地|年代中中生代的最後一o)
一o元的KY
at the end of an era
二Bo(古生代的最後一地|r代)
Q之 二Bo
known as the Permian.
三~x像b甲部一
Trilobites were armored animals that hunted
成群Y的在海床上肆虐
in great herds across the seafloor.
他是第一批M化出
They were among the first animals to evolve
可以成像的眼睛的游
image-forming eyes.
三~x繁s了大s2.7|年
Trilobites had a good long run, some 270 million years.
地球曾是三~x的天下
Earth was once the planet of the trilobites.
但他F在都]了 ^N了
But now they're all gone, extinct.
他中最後的一部分
The last of them were swept from life's stage
也S著其他物N一起
along with countless other species
在空前的h境碾y中^N了
in an unparalleled environmental disaster.
大碾yl生在今日西伯利的位置
The apocalypse began in what is now Siberia,
一鋈祟史上模o比巨大
with volcanic eruptions on a scale unlike anything
的火山l
in human experience.
那r地球很不一
Earth was very different then,
只有一超|大板K和一片大洋
with one single supercontinent and one great ocean.
o情的LC的熔Relentless floods of fiery lava
洪水般吞]了比西W大的^域
engulfed an area larger than Western Europe.
嗬mm的l持m了资f年
The pulsing eruptions went on for hundreds of thousands of years.
融化的岩石
The molten rock
c燃了煤 K且 污染了大
ignited coal deposits and polluted the air
充斥著二氧化碳和其他厥怏w
with carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases.
地球囟壬高 洋流停止了流
This heated the Earth and stopped the ocean currents from circulating.
有害的菌迅速繁殖
Noxious bacteria bloomed,
海中其他生物缀跞部缃^
but nearly everything else in the seas died.
腐臭的水散l出致命的硫化怏w
The stagnant waters belched deadly hydrogen sulfide gas into the air,
е麓蠖店地生物窒息
which suffocated most of the land animals.
百分之九十的物N缃^
Nine in ten of all species on the planet went extinct.
我Q之
We call it...
"大缃^"
The Great Dying.
地球上的生命差一c全部^N
Life on Earth came so near to being wiped out
需要花M上千f年才能恢
that it took more than ten million years to recover.
但是新的生命形式在慢慢M化
But new life-forms slowly evolved
_始填a由二Bo大屠⑦z留的空缺
to fill the openings left by the Permian holocaust.
恐就是其中的大A家
Among the biggest winners were the dinosaurs.
F在地球是他的天下
Now the Earth was their planet.
他的y治持m了1.5|年
Their reign continued for over 150 million years.
也是在一次大碾y中
Until it, too, came crashing down
不可避免的土崩瓦解
in another mass extinction.
地球上的生命奶古r期就受摧
Life on Earth has taken quite a beating over the eons.
s依然存在
And yet it's still there.
生命B得令人@
The tenacity of life is mind-boggling.
我是能找到一l意想不到的生存之路
We keep finding it where no one thought it could be.
看到那lo名走廊
That nameless corridor?
以後再f
That's for another day.
有N游锟梢曰钤诜序v的水中或者怨痰谋又
I know an animal that can live in boiling water or in solid ice.
可以10年不喝一滴水
It can go ten years without a drop of water.
可以不加防o的穿^寒冷真空
It can travel naked in the cold vacuum
K且充M烈射的太空 而毫op
and intense radiation of space and will return unscathed.
肢游 又叫  步游
The tardigrade, or water bear.
生活在最高的高山是最深的海
It's equally at home atop the tallest mountains
λ碚f]有^e
and in the deepest trenches of the sea.
他生活在苔\中  就在我周
And in our own backyards, where they live among the moss
狄挡磺
in countless numbers.
你可能]注意到他
You've probably never noticed them
因樗太小了
because they're so small.
差不多尖大小
About the size of a pinpoint.
但他很皂g
But they're tough.
肢游镌谒有的5次大碾y中存下
The tardigrades have survived all five mass extinctions.
而他t存在了5|年之久
They've been in business for a half a billion years.
我一直J樯命很挑剔
We used to think that life was finicky,
他只能接受
that it would only take hold where it was
不太冷 不太
not too hot, not too cold,
不太暗 不咸 不酸 ]射 的地方
not too dark or salty or acidic or radioactive.
有 不管怎N e忘了喝水
And whatever you do, don't forget to add water.
我e了
We were wrong.
肢游镒C明我e了
As the hardy tardigrade demonstrates,
生命可以承受人^o法生存的h境
life can endure conditions that would mean certain death for us humans.
但是我和那些生活在
But differences between us and life found
最O端h境下的生物
in even the most extreme environments on our planet
只有少S的^e
are only variations on a single theme,
就像一NZ言中的不同方言
dialects of a single language.
地球生命的z髅艽a
The genetic code of Earth life.
其他世界的生命又是什N拥哪
But what would life be like on other worlds?
有著完全不同v史的世界
Worlds with a completely different history,
和我完全不同的化W反和M化^程
chemistry and evolution from our planet?
我想你去一bh的世界
There's a distant world I want to take you to--
一和我@截然不同的世界
a world far different from our own,
可能藏有生命
but one that may harbor life.
如果有 那^ξ以前^的
If it does, it promises to be unlike anything
大不相同
we've ever seen before.
F完全包裹了泰坦的表面
Clouds and haze completely hide the surface of Titan,
即土l六
土星的大月亮
Saturn's giant moon.
泰坦和地球有c像
Titan reminds me a little bit of home.
他也有主要以氮饨M成的大
Like Earth, it has an atmosphere that's mostly nitrogen.
但是比我的稠密4倍
But it's four times denser.
空庵]有z毫氧
Titan's air has no oxygen at all.
比地球上任何地方都冷
And it's far colder than anywhere on Earth.
我依然想去那Y
But still... I want to go there.
我必下降
We have to descend
装俟里的F
through a couple hundred kilometers of smog
才能看到他的表面
before we can even see the surface.
但是下面藏著我熟悉的L景
But hidden beneath lies a weirdly familiar landscape.
泰坦是太系中除地球外唯一一下雨的地方
Titan is the only other world in the solar system where it ever rains.
它有著河流和海岸
It has rivers and coastlines.
有装湖泊
Titan has hundreds of lakes.
有一比北美的K必利湖大
One of them larger than Lake Superior in North America.
蒸汽暮面升起
Vapor rising from the lakes
凝Y落下成雨
condenses and falls again as rain.
就像地球一
The rain feeds rivers,
雨落M河流
which carve valleys into the landscape,
河流再⑸焦鹊窨坛鲲L景
just like on Earth.
但有一很大不同
But with one big difference.
泰坦上 海和雨不是由甲烷和乙烷M成
On Titan, the seas and the rain
而不是水
are made not of water but of methane and ethane.
在地球上 @些分子M成天然
On Earth, those molecules form natural gas.
在寒冷的泰坦上
On frigid Titan,
他是液B的
they're liquid.
泰坦上有很多水
Titan has lots of water,
但他都龅南袷^一佑
but all of it is frozen hard as rock.
事上 @些L景和山}
In fact, the landscape and mountains
都是水做的
are made mainly of water ice.
零下装俣
At hundreds of degrees below zero,
泰坦寒冷得永h不有液B的水
Titan is far too cold for water to ever be liquid.
天w生物W家一直在猜想
Astrobiologists since Carl Sagan have wondered
泰坦上的碳浠合物湖水中是否有生命
if life might swim in Titan's hydrocarbon lakes.
@N生命的化W成分
The chemical basis for such life
一定和我所知的都不一
would have to be entirely different from anything we know.
所有的地球生命都需要水
All life on Earth depends on liquid water.
泰坦的表面]有水
And Titan's surface has none of that.
但我可以想像另一N生命
But we can imagine other kinds of life.
@N生物可能呼吸
There might be creatures that inhale hydrogen
而不是氧
instead of oxygen.
呼出甲烷 而不是二氧化碳
And exhale methane instead of carbon dioxide.
乙炔可能是他的能量碓 而不是糖
They might use acetylene instead of sugar as an energy source.
我怎硬拍苷业剿
How could we find out if such creatures
如果他的帝躲藏在@石油般的海水下
rule a hidden empire beneath the oil-dark waves?
我下克拉肯海
We're diving down deep into the Kraken Sea,
@是以北W神中的挪威海怪命名
named for the mythic Norse sea monster.
就算真有海怪在@Y
Even if there is one of those down there,
我也看不到
we probably couldn't see it.
因樘黑了
It's so dark.
把地球上所有的石油和天然饧悠
If you took all the oil and natural gas on Earth,
也只是泰坦α康O小一部分
it would amount to but a tiny fraction of Titan's reserves.
我_c
Let's turn on some lights.
F在是表面下200米
We're now 200 meters beneath the surface.
看到什N了
Did you see something?
那 通道旁
Over there, by that vent.
也S我眼花了
Maybe it was just my imagination.
如果我想要_切知道的
I guess we'll have to come back
那N我就必得再硪淮
if we want to find out for sure.
我想和你再f最後一故事
There's one last story I want to tell you.
@是最ゴ蟮目W故事
And it's the greatest story science has ever told.
P於我世界上的生命
It's the story of life on our world.
g迎淼40|年前的地球
Welcome to the Earth of four billion years ago.
]有生命的星球
This was our planet before life.
]人知道生命如何Q生
Nobody knows how life got started.
撞艉颓治g摧Я舜蟛糠值淖C
Most of the evidence from that time was destroyed by impact and erosion.
科W在o知和已知之g
Science works on the frontier between knowledge and ignorance.
我不怕承J我不知道
We're not afraid to admit what we don't know.
一c也不G人
There's no shame in that.
G人的是我假b已有了答案
The only shame is to pretend that we have all the answers.
也S^中有人
Maybe someone watching this
成槭解_@i}的人
will be the first to solve the mystery
P於地球生命的起源
of how life on Earth began.
默F存的微生物得淼淖C@示
The evidence from living microbes
他最古老的祖先
suggest that their earliest ancestors
喜g高
preferred high temperatures.
地球生命也S出F在崴中
Life on Earth may have arisen in hot water
被水下的火山口h@著
around submerged volcanic vents.
在卡・_根的宇宙目中
In Carl Sagan's original Cosmos series,
他找到了
he traced the unbroken thread that stretches
⒔40|年前的渭胞生物到你之g的
directly from the one-celled organisms
不g嗟木索
of nearly four billion years ago... to you.
相於40秒的40|年
Four billion years in 40 seconds.
牟荒芊直夜的生物
From creatures who had yet to discern day from night
到可以探索宇宙的生物
to beings who are exploring the cosmos.
@就是分子用40|年rgM化的Y果
Those are some of the things that molecules do given four billion years of evolution.